History of Modern Astrophysics Collection 1849-1979 Mss.Ms.Coll.13
American Philosophical Society
History of Modern Astrophysics Collection
1849-1979
Mss.Ms.Coll.13
American Philosophical Society
2.0 Linear feet 2 linear feet; 67 reels of microfilm
During the mid- to late-1970s, the American Institute of Physics sponsored a project to conduct oral history interviews documenting the recent history of astrophysics, eventually accumulating over 400 hours of fully transcribed and edited audio tapes. The project organizers placed a particular emphasis on documenting the various subdisciplines of cosmology and astronomical spectroscopy. The History of Modern Astrophysics Collection is an important resource for the history of astrophysics in the latter half of the twentieth century. The collection is arranged in two series, the first consisting of transcripts of 52 interviews of 46 astrophysicists recorded between 1976 and 1979 by members of the Center for the History of Physics at the American Institute of Physics. The second series consists of 65 reels of microfilm of significant sets of correspondence for individual astrophysicists. The original oral history tape recordings are housed at AIP.
Center for History of Physics (American Institute of Physics)
Box 1-4
Reel 1-67
Bibliography
The HMA project is described in
Weart, Spencer R. and David H. DeVorkin, "Interviews as sources for history of Modern Astrophysics," Isis 72 (1981), 471-477.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Deposited by the American Institute of Physics through Spencer R. Weart, 1982 (accn. no. 1982-1024ms).
Scope and Contents note
The History of Modern Astrophysics Collection is an important resource for the history of astrophysics in the latter half of the twentieth century. The collection is arranged in two series, the first consisting of transcripts of 52 interviews of 46 astrophysicists recorded between 1976 and 1979 by members of the Center for the History of Physics at the American Institute of Physics. The second series consists of 65 reels of microfilm of significant sets of correspondence for individual astrophysicists. The original oral history tape recordings are housed at AIP.
Biographical/Historical note
During the mid- to late-1970s, the Center for the History of Physics of the American Institute of Physics sponsored an oral history project designed to provide a systematic survey of late 20th century astrophysics. Slightly adjusting the model provided by the successful Sources for the History of Quantum Physics, the History of Modern Astrophysics project slightly deemphasized detailed inquiry into early scientific work, while delving more deeply into personal and social matters. Like the Quantum Physics project, they also sought out and microfilmed significant bodies of records, particularly those for observatories, that were deemed to be "in danger, or in remote locations, or of exceptional value to a broad community of scholars."
The initial list of candidates for interviews was compiled based upon recommendations that emerged from a series of exploratory interviews with astrophysicists, supplemented by individuals who were frequently cited in review articles, who were the recipients of major astronomical prizes, or who were mentioned as significant contributors in the existing secondary literature. These were then ranked and submitted to an advisory panel of historians of astronomy to fill in any omissions. Given the limitations of such a large undertaking, the project organizers inevitably chose to emphasize certain fields at the expense of others. In particular, they limited the number of interviews with radio astronomers and solar system astrophysics because these subfields were covered under other projects, while they sought extensive coverage of a variety of subfields in cosmology. Approximately 25% of the interviews were with cosmologists and a slightly smaller number concerned astronomical spectroscopy. The selection of subjects for interviews was also biased geographically: over half of the subjects were born and educated in the United States, with Britain, the Netherlands, and Germany relatively well represented, but the Soviet Union notably underrepresented.
Ultimately, the project logged over 400 hours of interviews with over 100 astronomers, resulting in over 10,000 pages of edited transcripts. Following the standard procedures established at the AIP, the interviews were fully transcribed and edited against the tape by the interviewer before being sent to the astronomer for further editing and permissions. Several different interviewers were employed during the project, including interviewers who were not members of the AIP staff.
Abell, George (George Ogden), 1927-1983; Aitken, Douglas Carryl; American Institute of Physics.; Atkinson, Robert d'Escourt, 1898-1982; Babcock, Horace W.; Bondi, Hermann; Bowyer, Stuart C.; Chandler, Seth Carlo, 1846-1913; Chandrasekhar, S. (Subrahmanyan), 1910-; Chang, Y. C.; Conklin, Nanielov Dieter; Cowling, T. G. (Thomas George); Dunham, Theodore J., 1897-1984; Edmonson, Frank K., (Frank Kelly), 1912-; Greenstein, Jesse L., (Jesse Leonard), 1909-2002; Hall, John; Hayes, D. S., (Donald S.); Herget, Paul, 1908-; Hoffleit, Dorrit; Hogg, Helen Sawyer, 1905-; Hubble, Edwin Powell, 1889-1953; Huffer, Charles M. (Charles Morse), 1894-; Hulst, H. C. Van de (Hendrik Christoffell), 1918-; Jones, Burton Wadsworth, 1902-; Kharadze, Yevgeny Kirillovich; King, Ivan R.; Kron, Gerald E.; Kron, Richard G.; Leighton, Robert B.; Locanthi, Dorothy Davis; Massevitch, Alla Genrikhovna; Mayall, N. U. (Nicholas Ulrich), 1906-; McCrea, William Hunter; McVittie, George C., (George Cunliffe); Münch, Guido, 1921-; O'Connell, D. J. K. (Daniel Joseph Kelly); Oort, Jan Hendrik; Plaskett, Harry Hemley, 1893-1980; Rossi, Bruno Benedetto, 1905-; Russell, Henry Norris, 1877-1957; Salpeter, Edwin E.; Schatzman, Evry L.; Schlesinger, Frank, 1871-1943; Sciama, D. W. (Dennis William), 1926-; Shapiro, Bert; Shapley, Harlow, 1885-1972; Spinrad, Hyron, 1934-; Spitzer, Lyman, 1914-1997; Struve, Otto, 1897-1963; Swings, P., (Polydore), 1906-1983; Tinsley, Beatrice; Unsöld, Albrecht, 1905-1995; Van Agt, Steven; Vassilevskis, Stanislaus; Wesselink, Adriaan Jan, 1909-1995; Young, Charles Augustus, 1834-1908; Astronomical spectroscopy.; Astrophysicists.; Astrophysics; Cosmology; Galaxies--Evolution; Oral histories; Quasars; Radio astrophysics; Stars--Evolution
- Series I. Oral histories, 1976-1979; 52 files
  - Abell, George. Interview conducted by Spencer Weart, 1977 November (Box 1)
  - Aitken, Douglas Carryl. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 July (Box 1)
  - Babcock, Horace W., Interview conducted by Spencer Weart, 1977 July (Box 1)
  - Bondi, Herman. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin (Box 1)
  - Bowyer, C. Stuart. Interview conducted by Richard Hirsch, 1976 July (Box 1)
  - Chandrasekhar, Subrahmanyan. Interview conducted by Spencer Weart, 1977 May (Box 1)
  - Chang, Y. C., Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1979 August (Box 1)
  - Conklin, Nanielou Dieter. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 July (Box 1)
  - Cowling, Thomas George. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1978 March (Box 1)
  - Edmonson, Frank K., Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 April (Box 1)
  - Edmonson, Frank K., Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1978 February (Box 1)
  - Greenstein, Jesse. Interview conducted by Spencer Weart, 1977 April (Box 1)
  - Greenstein, Jesse. Interview conducted by Spencer Weart, 1977 July (Box 1)
  - Greenstein, Jesse. Interview conducted by Spencer Weart, 1978 May (Box 1)
  - Hall, John. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1979 February (Box 1)
  - Hayes, Donald S., Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 November (Box 1)
  - Herget, Paul. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 April (Box 1)
  - Hoffleit, Dorrit. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1979 August (Box 1)
  - Hogg, Helen Sawyer. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1979 August (Box 1)
  - Huffer, C. M., Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 July (Box 1)
  - Hulst, Hendrik Christoffell van de. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1978 July (Box 1)
  - Jones, Burton. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 July (Box 1)
  - Kharadze, Yevgeny Kirillovich. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1979 August (Box 1)
  - King, Ivan. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 July (Box 1)
  - King, Ivan. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1978 July (Box 1)
  - Kron, Gerald. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1979 May (Box 1)
  - Kron, Richard. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 July (Box 1)
  - Leighton, R. B., Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 July (Box 1)
  - Locanthi, Dorothy Davis. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 August (Box 1)
  - Masevitch, Alla Genrikhovna. Interview conducted by Spencer Weart, 1976 September (Box 1)
  - Mayall, Nicholas U., Interview conducted by Bert Shapiro, 1976 June (Box 1)
  - Mayall, Nicholas U., Interview conducted by Norris Heatherington, 1977 February (Box 1)
  - McCrea, William Hunter. Interview conducted by Robert Smith, 1978 September (Box 1)
  - McVittie, George Cunliffe. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1978 March (Box 1)
  - Munch, Guido. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 July (Box 1)
  - O'Connell, Daniel Joseph Kelly. Interview conducted by Spencer Weart, 1976 August (Box 1)
  - Oort, Jan H., Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 November (Box 1)
  - Plaskett, Harry Hemley. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1978 March (Box 1)
  - Rossi, Bruno. Interview conducted by Richard Hirsch, 1976 July (Box 1)
  - Russell, Henry Norris, Jr., Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 November (Box 1)
  - Salpeter, Edwin E., Interview conducted by Spencer Weart, 1978 March (Box 1)
  - Schatzman, Evry. Interview conducted by Spencer Weart, 1979 August (Box 1)
  - Sciama, Dennis. Interview conducted by Spencer Weart, 1978 March (Box 1)
  - Shapiro, Bert. Interview, 1977 July (Box 1)
  - Spinrad, Hyron. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 July (Box 1)
  - Spitzer, Lyman. Interview conducted by Joan Brumberg, 1978 May (Box 1)
  - Tinsley, Beatrice. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 June (Box 1)
  - Unsold, Albrecht. Interview conducted by Owen Gingerich, 1978 June (Box 1)
  - Van Agt, Steven. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 November (Box 1)
  - Vassilevskis, Stanislaus. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 July (Box 1)
  - Wesselink, A. J. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1977 September (Box 1)
  - Wesselink, A. J. Interview conducted by David DeVorkin, 1978 June (Box 1)
- Series II. Microfilms, 1849-1979; 67 reels
  - Papers, 1927-1955; 1 reel; Atkinson, Robert d'Escourt, 1898-1982 (Reel 1)
  - Papers, 1861-1914; 1 reel; Chandler, Seth Carlo, 1846-1913 (Reel 2)
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    Microfilmed from originals in possession of the family.
  - Papers, 1921-1979; 3 reels; Dunham, Theodore J., 1897-1984 (Reel 3-5)
    Originals at APS (Ms. Coll. 40).
  - Papers, 1 reel; Edmonson, Frank K., (Frank Kelly), 1912- (Reel 6)
  - Papers, 1900-1960; 1 reel; Hubble, Edwin Powell, 1889-1953 (Reel 7)
    Originals at Huntington Library, San Marino, Calif.
  - Papers, 1926-1975; 1 reel; McVittie, George C., (George Cunliffe) (Reel 8)
    Originals at University of Illinois Archives.
  - Papers, 1927-1956; 1 reel; Oort, Jan Hendrik (Reel 9)
    Originals at Leiden University, Netherlands.
  - Papers, 1905-1941; 31 reels; Schlesinger, Frank, 1871-1943 (Reel 10-40)
    Originals at University of Pittsburgh and Yale University
  - Papers, 1910-1923; 3 reels; Shapley, Harlow, 1885-1972 (Reel 41-43)
    Originals at Harvard University Archives.
  - Papers, 1932-1945; 16 reels; Struve, Otto (Reel 44-59)
    Originals in Yerkes Observatory Archives, University of Chicago
  - Correspondence with Otto Struve, 1932-1963; 3 reels; Swings, P., (Polydore), 1906-1983 (Reel 60-62)
    Originals in possession of the family at the time of filming.
  - Papers, 1849-1908; 3 reels; Young, Charles A. (Reel 63-65)
    Originals at Dartmouth College Archives.
  - Oral history transcripts: Abel-King, 1 reel (Reel 66)
  - Oral history transcripts: Kron-Wood, 1 reel (Reel 67)